sorry everyone a little more light on
the situation here welcome to the March
QA glad to see you all here thanks for
tuning in so let's see if we can get
somewhere reasonable today I guess I
could update you a little bit if you'd
be interested tell you what has been
going on my wife Tammy and I came back
from Australia New Zealand at the end of
February we had a really good tour there
I would say about a dozen places maybe
15 hard to keep track as we went to a
number of places more than once large
crowds some of the bigger venues
Melbourne for example is 5500 people so
I think that was the biggest audience
that I had spoken to independently of
the discussions with sam harris so that
was very interesting to see that crowds
of that magnitude would show up got to
speak at the Sydney Opera House which
was extremely exciting you know it's
such an iconic building so that was a
real honor it's been like that for lots
of the theaters that I've been in you
know these old iconic buildings that so
many people have performed in it's quite
a privilege to be able to get backstage
and take a look
we enjoyed Australia and New Zealand a
lot the company tagged a tea that hosted
it hosted the tour did an outstanding
job and the press even was reasonably
welcoming I would say at least in
Australia and New Zealand it was a bit
of a different story they seem to be
more polarized there as recent events
have clearly indicated so since I've
been back well I haven't been
particularly productive I've mostly been
sleeping as it turns out so I guess I've
worn out after a year of touring but I'm
hard at work on my next book tentatively
entitled beyond order or beyond mere
order twelve more rules for life I'm up
to chapter nine and I would say I'm
pretty stuck on it at the moment I'm
I'm having a hard time slogging through
it brain isn't as sharp as it could be
and have to be sharp to edit so anyway
some set up some new offices this is
this week to get my team together for
the online education project so that's
exciting about five of us that will be
working together in some offices with a
company called post media who I'm also
working with writing journal newspaper
articles so that's exciting and we're
hoping for good things from the online
education program no timelines or
anything like that
still it's a complicated system I've
been working as well on the patreon
replacement that's looking really good I
would say I met with the developer this
week we're hoping well we're hoping to
have some of it functional by April 1st
and they'll be a little bit more
information about that available act on
April 1st I have a talk in New York on
April 17th at the Beacon Theater I think
it's sold out I have a talk on April
19th at the Sony Centre in Toronto with
Slava Dziedzic who's probably the
world's most famous Marxist philosopher
and so that should be interesting and
challenging and hopefully productive and
then for those of you who might be
watching from the UK or from somewhere
reasonably accessible to the UK I am
doing at 12 rules for life lecture tour
show may 8th in London which is the same
time that the paperback version of 12
rules for life is coming up so that's
basically that for updates
I guess now maybe there's a bit more
i've videotaped a number of my lectures
in australia which is the first time
i've done that professionally videotaped
them I think I taped six and so we'll be
releasing them in some form yet to be
determined maybe on the new platform in
the
relatively new future and I have about
50 of them 55 of them audio taped and
transcribed and so I've put together the
transcriptions it's about a million
words and I'm hoping that there's
possibly books I can derive from that
but if there's not folks there's
certainly podcasts and that sort of
thing so and I have a lot of interviews
coming up as well so that's what's
happening on this end of the universe
so let's take some questions and see how
that goes
so I don't know why this question is so
popular but and it's completely
ridiculous but that's okay
Stephen shudders who obviously hasn't
got anything better to do
wants to know what is my favorite soup
and apparently 333 people are also
interested in that particular topic and
I would say it's actually irrelevant
unfortunately because I don't eat soup
I'm on this crazy on meat diet that some
of you know about and that doesn't go
along very well with soup but if I had
to pick a soup that I ate at one point
my favorite soup was a clam chowder that
I used to make with corn and I was a
dish I was particularly proud of I was
actually not a bad cook I spent a lot of
time cooking in restaurants and really
enjoyed it and miss it a lot the
diversity you know of cuisine and so it
would have to be clam chowder so now you
know the most important thing about me
that you could possibly know when will
you be starting back up your Bible
series well that's a good question and
it looks like it'll be the fall now
what's happening in October is that I'm
going to Cambridge University in the UK
for two months and I'm going to be a
visiting fellow there at the Divinity
School and that should give me an
opportunity to talk to religious experts
of all types for a couple of months as
well as students
and the plan at the moment is to do that
at the same time that I start recording
the lectures on Exodus so I figured I
could kill two birds with one stone that
way I could start the biblical lectures
again which I'm really looking forward
to and also update my biblical knowledge
substantially as well as having the
opportunity to spend some time in
Cambridge which I think would be really
exciting I was there a little bit this
summer and it's known absolutely
beautiful University and it's quite a
thrill for someone who's academically
minded to be to be their period but also
to be invited there too to sit in and
participate for a couple of months and
so anyways maybe I can get 10 or so
lectures out in that period of time
let's say if I did one a week I'm not
exactly sure how I'm going to do it if
I'm gonna rent a public theater like I
did in Toronto I think that's probably
the plan
but anyways assume October or November
that's the that's the plan at the moment
what I'm trying to concentrate on right
now is finishing my new book which has a
relatively sudden or you know relatively
it has a due date that's in the
relatively recent future and so I like
to stay on top of those things it's easy
to get behind when you're writing a book
and to rush it and to do it badly and so
I'm trying to make sure that I've got my
priorities straight so anyways that's
the situation with the biblical series
I'm really looking forward to it I think
one of the most worthwhile things I've
done in my academic career was that
series on Genesis and I learned a
tremendous amount and so I'm assuming
the same thing will happen with the
Exodus stories which I know better so
that should be slightly easier on me
from a rate of learning perspective and
hopefully I'll be able to go deeper
because they are really remarkable
stories so I've also been struck by the
you know the reception to those biblical
stories I've read
surprising number for example of a
surprising number for example of letters
from Islamic viewers who've been
watching them and the letters have been
very positive and so that's that's made
me think very hard about the overall
potential effect of delineating the
meaning of all these old stories I think
that to the degree that we want to
preserve the understructure of our
culture and I regard that as grounded in
judeo-christian tradition very very
firmly as well as other traditions
obviously the greco-roman tradition
probably foremost among them the stories
have to be brought alive again and I
don't think there's any more effective
way of demonstrating their utility than
to make them come alive Mir what your
profession of belief and value isn't
sufficient one thing you might guys
might be interested in to it this is a
video or a an audio I think I don't know
if I videotaped this one or just audio
recorded it I did a lecture in Australia
on this question about belief in God and
why I'm not very happy about the
question and unwilling in some sense to
answer it so I did in to our snow 70
minute lecture on how that question why
that question is problematic for me and
what can be done about it
what what the proper answer is to it I
think so hopefully you'll find something
interesting in that when it's finally
released
I do not attend church how can I teach
my children the biblical stories in a
productive way without the dogma or
little and literal interpretation of
organized religion well that's an
unbelievably complicated problem and I
actually don't know the answer to it I'm
not sure that I did a particularly good
job of teaching my children the biblical
stories in a productive way without the
dogma or literal interpretation of
organized
religion I think that you could start by
just reading them the stories you know
there are decent plain English
translations of the biblical stories and
you might find that just reading the
stories to them at least they're
familiar with them that way and you'd
have to pick and choose obviously
because they're not going to be too
thrilled by sitting through endless
genealogies but there are also biblical
translations available that put the
stories out in prose form and do a
pretty good job of editing out the
genealogical material and the other
things that might not be so what might
not capture the imagination of children
particularly well I can't think of any
better way of doing it than just reading
the stories to them and perhaps to the
degree that it's possible to discuss
them and see if that works
maybe it'll work maybe it won't I mean I
didn't take my kids to church you know
having stopped attending really when I
was 13 and I have my reasons for not
attending maybe they're good and maybe
they're not I very back and forth with
that one of the downsides of that was
that though they didn't develop the same
familiarity with the stories that I had
developed when I was a kid because I did
go to church fairly regularly until I
was 13 and it's it's definitely a loss
my cynicism about church organization
it's it's cynicism I don't know what it
is exactly well I didn't do my
children's education on the biblical
front any good so I'm still at sixes and
sevens let's say about that and about
exactly what to do about it but you
could try reading I'm reading the
stories to them and see how that goes
and there are children's versions
available as well you know what I
suspect if you look carefully on Amazon
you could find ones that were well
reviewed and so that might be another
way of approaching it what question are
you asked way too seldom
oh well that's pretty easy at least if
if the question is what question am I
asked by journalists way too seldom and
the answer to that would be dr. Peterson
what the hell is going on and what I
mean by that is why are so many people
coming to your lectures let's say and
why did your book strike such a chord I
think the first one is the most
important one you know generally what
happens with with journalists is that
they're very cynical about what is
happening at my lectures and also who's
attending and it's really very
pejorative demeaning thoughtless
prejudiced and I would say cruel all at
once because the first assumption is
that you know I'm talking primarily to
angry white young man and there
certainly isn't a lot of evidence for
that I would say the average age of the
people in my audience is 30s and that's
not exactly young and then I would say
well it's at least 30% women and that's
been increasing as the book has sold
more and you know the reason it was men
primarily to begin with I think is
because well there are many men starving
for an encouraging voice and also the
fact that YouTube which is where I
picked up my primary audience to begin
with skews about 8020 male to female in
terms of its viewership which really
doesn't have anything to do with me
right that's just a what do you call
that that's a baseline phenomena that
has to be taken into phenomenon that has
to be taken into account before you make
any but before you draw any conclusions
about the nature of someone's audience
but the presumption is is that you
I'm speaking politically and in a
divisive way to the people who show up
to my to my lectures into my talks and
I'm just not true the lectures aren't
political except peripherally I mean you
now and then throw a critical comment or
two out about the manner in which this
strange alliance of post-modernism and
neo Marxism has been dominating the
university but I think that's perfectly
reasonable thing to point out apart from
that the lecture is almost all
concentrate on psychological
self-improvement and it seems almost
impossible for the media to be not
cynical about that you know I think it's
partly because almost everything that
the classic media covers has to be
politicized and I was on a show for
example called Q&A in Australian show
which was it's their biggest political
show it's modeled on one in the UK which
is also quite big which I was also on a
while back and every issue immediately
becomes discussed among polarized
political lines it's as if our discourse
has degenerated to the point where the
only possible response to a question
about anything important has to be
ideological so left or right and it has
to be political and so I think part of
the problem is perhaps that the
phenomenon that constitutes the
attendance at my lectures
doesn't fit the standard news media
narrative which is driven by journalists
I think who had political ambitions
fundamentally or still have political
ambitions of one sort or another and who
tend to view worldly through a political
means but for me the experience of my
lectures is actually an unbelievably
positive one and and not particularly
stressful like it's nowhere near as
stressful as almost any interview I have
with almost any journalist
because again things get politicized
very rapidly what happens in the
lectures is that you know 3,000 people
show up and they're happy to be there
and so it's a very welcoming atmosphere
and I get to talk to them for 70 minutes
about some psychological problem I would
say often associated with one of the
chapters in my book like what it means
to what what a human competence
hierarchy might look like say if I was
talking about chapter 1 because we do
organize hierarchies human beings
naturally organize hierarchies like
other animals too but we tend to
organize hierarchies to achieve valuable
goals you know valuable in that their
goals that people assume would be
usefully achieved to decrease the some
amount of suffering in the world or
maybe to bring happiness to people or a
bit of luxury or something generally
something of at least limited use and
often far more than limited you know and
I talked to people about the fact that
the best way to make progress in human
hierarchy has nothing to do with power
but everything to do with reciprocity
and responsibility I just read this or
watched this really cool TED talk I
think it was a TED talk by friends de
Waal FR ANS de wal and he studied
political behavior in chimpanzees so I
wish I had the URL for it maybe somebody
can post that if they would but one of
the things that do all pointed out was
that the most impact
chimpanzees in a chimpanzee troop are
actually the dominant the most dominant
males they're the ones who do the most
comforting and the most care like the
females are more empathic than the males
on average but across all of the
chimpanzees the most dominant males are
the ones that show the most empathic
responses and that's part of their walls
and he's not the only animal ethologist
someone who studies the natural behavior
of animals
he's not the only person to point this
sort of thing out you know is that the
ability to move forward in a hierarchy
is dependent on far more than power and
aggression and it's dependent on
reciprocity and friendship but also
especially in the case of human beings
on skill because hopefully when we
organize our hierarchies and we're
attempting to solve complex problems by
setting up a hierarchy that allows for
competition and cooperation that the
hierarchy organizes itself so that the
most competent people rise to the top
and I actually think that generally
speaking that's true I mean the
selection process isn't perfect and it's
marred by you could say the proclivity
to select people for reasons other than
their fundamental competence and that
might be their attractiveness or their
extraversion or their height or their
charisma their self-confidence it might
be their race or their gender their
sexuality - in situations where a true
prejudice plays a role but that only
happens when the hierarchies have become
corrupt because obviously it's in
everyone's best interests if we're
trying to solve complex problems that
the most competent people are the ones
that have the opportunity to rise to the
top and I actually think we do a damn
good job of that in the West which is
why almost everything that we do in the
West works why everything is reliable
and why the power is always on and why
our electronic technology works and why
our society in general works you can be
cynical about that if you want but I
don't know what you would compare the
functionality of our societies to
because things are way better than they
were a hundred and fifty years ago
they're getting better very very rapidly
as Western ideas of production and
private property and an honesty and
integrity I would say as well spread
around the world especially now that the
more radical socialist ideas that were
pushed by people like the the Soviets
have have declined at least to some
degree since the collapse of the Soviet
Union well anyways this is the sort of
thing that's discussed at the talks you
know
or that's rule one and we know rule two
I talked to people about taking care of
themselves like there's someone who they
have responsibility for and that's not a
political issue - it's it's it's an
injunction - assuming that you have a
certain intrinsic value you know and
that it's necessary for that value to
manifest itself for you to push yourself
against the world to challenge yourself
because otherwise what you're capable of
won't manifest itself it has to be
developed it has to be called forth by
necessity right you have to pick a hard
problem and try to solve it and push
yourself against it in order for and you
have to try to do that truthfully and
responsibly in order for what it is that
you're intrinsically capable of and
composed of to come to the forefront and
that seems like a very positive thing as
far as I'm concerned to encourage people
to be responsible for themselves and for
other people and also to point out that
that you have a moral responsibility to
do so for yourself just as you do for
others and I I think that that message
has been very helpful to people at least
that's what they've told me and it's
predicated the rule is predicated on the
old judeo-christian idea of the oldest
idea in some sense that you know that
there's a relationship between logos
which is truthful speech and
communication and bringing things into
being from chaotic potential that's the
idea that's put forward in Genesis and
also the idea that men and women alike
are made in the image of God which
suggests that like God we have the
capability of affecting potential
affecting the possible future and
turning it into the actual present and
that we do that at least in part as a
consequence of our ethical choices you
know and then I'll give you one more
example in rule 10 which is be precise
in your speech I point out that a
tremendous that
the aims that you have in your life the
ethical aims and those are the aims that
direct your actions also direct your
perceptions that this is true at a neuro
physiological level and that much of the
way that the world manifests itself to
you is a consequence of the structure of
your ethics so it's your ethical
structure that's instantiated
neurophysiological II that serves as an
intermediary between the world of
phenomena let's say objective phenomena
and your perception of that and you see
the world through an ethical lens and
one of the things that that suggests and
I outlined this in rule 6 is that if the
world looks to you like a dismal and
terrible place and you're nihilistic and
depressed and hopeless and all of that I
mean there can be physiological reasons
for that you might be ill but if it's a
psychological issue it's certainly
possible that at least part of the
reason that everything appears to you in
that light is because your ethical
structure is not well formulated its
incoherent
its nihilistic it isn't predicated on
the idea for example that people have
some some spark of divine virtue and
that everyone is valuable in that right
and that we all have the possibility to
make a genuine contribution to the world
or at least to stop it from degenerating
any more than it has to into a kind of
hell so anyways that's a very long
answer to that question but it is see
it's so interesting to me that the
journalists who interview me have no
curiosity about why it is that so many
people are coming to watch my lectures
they it's like the curiosity has been
boiled out of them in some sense because
it certainly makes me curious I've every
time I go on stage and there's 3,500
people there I'm curious about why
they're there and so we have a
discussion about all these things that
I've been talking about and I can tell
you too that the one thing that really
brings the house to a dead silence which
is very much worth
attention to is the discussion anytime I
have a discussion about the relationship
between responsibility and meaning you
know because one of the fundamental
theses of 12 rules for life and also of
maps of meaning is that because life is
essentially tragic in its fundamental
essence you need a sustaining meaning
that's deep and and profound and and
deep and profound enough to get you
through bad times because there will be
very bad times in your life there'll be
death and they'll be illness and they'll
be disappointment of of all sorts and
and there'll be just the standard
difficulties of life in the world to
contend with and you really must have
something that's profound and powerful
to set up against that and I think that
your voluntary adoption of the struggle
to improve being is the proper antidote
to that and and that the best way to do
that is to live responsibly and
truthfully I truly believe that and I
think that people know this you know
because when I talk to my audiences
about exactly this about who they admire
for example you know it's like well you
don't admire people who lie and cheat
and deceive if you don't teach your
children to do that
you admire people who keep their word
who are honest and reliable and you want
them around especially in times of
trouble and you want people who are
capable of being responsible for
themselves and to take care of
themselves properly as if they matter as
a moral duty and then you also want
people who have extended themselves past
that so that they can take care of their
family and regard that as a noble and
appropriate enterprise and who are
reliable for their children and for
their husbands and wives and then you
want people who are capable of extending
themselves even beyond that and taking
care of the community and when I talk
about that and that's meaning 3 find the
meaning in your life if you're if you're
looking for it it's not in happiness and
it's not an impulsive pleasure none of
that works for any length of time
well it tends to kick back hard and it's
certainly not something that's going to
get you through rough times it's the
ability to pick up a heavy load of
responsibility and to move forward with
it and what's so interesting is that
every time I talk about this with my
audiences they're reduced to complete
silence and there's I think there's
something and then that's you know I've
noticed that in a hundred and fifty
different cities now and it's something
you really have to take seriously when
you see it happening over and over and I
do believe that a huge part of the
reason that people are coming to watch
my lectures and to buy my book
the lectures of course have more direct
impact on me than the book sales
although the book sales now have
approached three million copies which is
quite something in hardcover around the
world and they're not translated into
all the languages they're going to be
translated into that's I think 50
languages is what they're slated for now
but the lectures have more impact on me
because I get to see the audience and
then to talk to people afterwards you
know when they tell me the same thing
many people who come up to me in the
meet and greets because people can come
and talk to me after the after the
lecture there's special tickets arranged
for that that's handled by a particular
company and they tell me you know
they've been trying to develop a vision
for their life and to act more
responsibility and to speak more
truthfully and to take more
responsibility maybe I already said that
and that the changes in their lives have
been overwhelming as a consequence
merely trying to just speak the truth or
not lie has had a huge effect on many of
the people that I've talked to and it's
not a simple thing to do you know and
it's a risky thing because the
consequences of speaking the truth in
the short term especially if you're not
very practiced at it can be quite
devastating which is of course why
people don't do it but the medium to
long term consequences are extremely
beneficial and it's what sets the world
straight and so what question are you
asked way too seldom
well dr. Peterson don't you think that
it's interesting that so many people are
coming to your lectures that are
fundamentally psychological and
philosophical in nature and apparently
doing so because they're really trying
hard to get their lives together it's
like yeah I think that's really
interesting and it's a question that's
really worth pursuing it's the only
question that's worth pursuing as far as
I'm concerned because it's a real
mystery that there's such a demand for
this I can't I can't fathom it I think
it's it's being a source of tremendous
optimism to me that people have that
burning desire for a more profound
dialogue and you know it's not
necessarily the people that you expect
to so the journalists you know they're
very cynical about my hypothetically
angry audience for example and you know
I've spoken now to I think three hundred
and fifty thousand people right three
hundred and fifty thousand people in a
hundred and fifty cities and we haven't
had one episode of misbehavior from
anybody in the audience except for one
person who stood up in some City and had
a few you know rebellious things to say
but they that person wasn't a partisan
of mine by any stretch of the
imagination
the lectures of being very very peaceful
and they're very very positive and
that's part of the reason why I've been
able to travel around so regularly over
the last year with my wife and do 150
lectures you know cuz it's quite well
demanding all that traveling and all
that thinking because each of the
lectures is different at least the
degree that I can make it but they're so
positive and it's so exciting at a
fundamental level to see people want to
engage in serious dialogue of that sort
that it's unbelievably sustaining let's
call it that it makes up for the inner
to use Australia tired me out I think
I've maybe did do a bit too much
travelling around and you know there
were some other issues in my family that
had to be dealt with in January and
March that were quite serious and so
that was another issue that that was
draining let's say but I'll tell you
both my wife and I am Dave Rubin - and
and my tour manager John O'Connell who's
been a really good guy you know we've
all found this entire experience
extraordinarily positive and are the
same thing happens with the people who
are arranging the tours it's their
experiences is the same so how to
balance between making peace and
speaking the truth in intimate relations
what if truth hurts the other or two
sides conflict well you can be
absolutely certain that that's going to
happen I mean look the first thing
that's a really good question
that's from Vincent it's a really good
question it's a really difficult
question the first thing you have to
decide is this goes back to what I was
discussing about 10 minutes ago about
what your aims are you know your whole
the whole way you perceive the world is
dependent on what you're on the aim of
your ethical structure and so that
ethical structure is is a it's a
hierarchy with something at the top
that's of crucial importance and Carl
Jung would say that whatever is at the
top of your ethical hierarchy functions
psychologically as if it's God for you
it's because it's the highest of all
possible values and you can think of God
in that sense as a personality that
perhaps a personality that you're trying
to mimic because a value structure
actually constitutes a personality that
you're trying to act out or mimic and so
the highest element in that personality
structure would be the most valuable
portion of that personality you might
say well what do you
want what do you want if you could have
what you wanted if you could knock in
the door would open so to speak and if
you could ask and you would receive what
would you want and and that means what
would you give what would you give what
would you be willing to give up
important things for how would you
prioritize which is the same as giving
up important things and it's not easy to
come to terms with what you want because
you might be angry and resentful and
bitter and you might have your reasons
for that and and that might contaminate
your ethical structure let's say and
make it so that there's large parts of
you that would be the shadow part from
the Union perspectives who's actually
that are actually after conflict and and
harm and cruelty and suffering out of
spite and revenge and then the
probability that part of you is like
that is unbelievably high because it's
it's very hard to be pure of spirit
let's say given how much suffering and
malevolence there is in the world and
how much were exposed to that so it's
very easy to take the low road if you if
you are married let's say or you have a
close relationship with someone and you
want that relationship to be good then
the first thing that you have to figure
out is well what do you mean by good you
know so and I would say well good would
be loving let's say and what that would
mean is that each of you would be trying
to take care of the other and yourself
as if you're of equal import and that
that import is high and so I think that
once you're married to someone for
example or once you have children and
then maybe this the same thing applies
to your immediate family your parents
and your siblings is that probably
somewhat less so for them although still
significantly that you have to treat
your spouse and your children as if they
are yourself and I know that's an old
idea and it's not often explained well
but
you you well that also assumes that what
you want for yourself is something
approximating what would be best for you
and you'd have to figure that out as
well and I don't know it seems to me
that well you want to like the people
that you're with and so you have to
treat them well and you want them to
love you and to love them
I would say at least to the same degree
that you'd want that from a pet you know
it's very nice to come home if you have
a dog or another animal that loves you
to have something there that's really on
your side that's happy to see you it's
one of the wonderful things that can
happen well in a marriage but also when
you have children so you want to like
the people you're around you want to
love them you want to support them when
they're having a hard time and vice
versa so you want to make your the
vessel in which your family's ensconced
watertight and and capable of
withstanding storms you want to
discipline yourself so that you're not
doing things that you're ashamed of you
want to tell the truth you want to work
responsibly and be a good provider
whether you're female or male in
whatever capacity you can manage and I
would say that also goes for children to
the degree that they're capable of
contributing to the family environment
and you have to think that all through
you want to embed your family in a
healthy social life too and in a healthy
community life but that all has to be
conscious and thought through before you
can start telling the truth
know how to balance between making peace
and speaking truth in intimate
relationships
what if truth hurts the other or two
sides conflict okay so the first thing
you have to do is with the person that
you're communicating with you both have
to figure out well what it is it what
are you aiming at you know I think it's
in rule 9 which is assume that the
person you're listening to knows
something that you don't that I outlined
a number of different conversational
types you know and there's the
conversational type that's
designed to mutually amuse and that can
be lots of fun and there's the
conversational type that's designed to
win that's where I have a point of view
and you have a point of view and and we
engage in a power dispute especially
essentially a Dominus dispute where the
goal is for one of the positions to come
out on top and win and then there's
another conversation where the goal is
to explore a problem and to come to a
joint to jointly further the
understanding of that problem and I
would say that that's how you balance
making peace and speaking the truth in
intimate relationships is that you know
the first thing you have to do is well
you have to have a conversation about
just exactly what the problem is
and that might take a long time and a
lot of listening because when people are
upset about something they don't always
know what it is that they're upset about
and what they're upset about might be
associated with a hundred other things
that they're upset about that they've
not dealt with and some of those can be
directly germane to the issue at hand
but some of them can be a consequence of
Oh old family trouble or old trauma to
use a very overused word but trouble in
the past that hasn't been dealt with
properly and it all amalgamates into a
complex that's the psychoanalytic idea
that consists of all the problems that
the person is dealing with that haven't
been resolved and then any new problem
gets it gets it's poorly separated from
that entire complex of problems and so
when the person is upset then all the
things they're upset about can sort of
manifest themselves in in a incoherent
and chaotic manner and that's really
hard and so if someone's upset about
something you or the other person might
take a tremendous amount of listening
before you can even get to what the
problem is and often during that process
of listening there's a lot of mutual
recrimination and accusations as each
person tries to work
because if you're annoyed at someone and
maybe all the other things that are
wrong with your life are in the
background driving the annoyance but you
don't really know it you're gonna accuse
them of all sorts of misbehavior some of
it know with some justification no doubt
and all sorts of inadequacies it's not a
good way of communicating but it happens
a lot and then that person has to defend
themselves like mad just so that they
can not be the target of all that
vitriol that's stored up for such a
tremendous length of time so anyways you
have to listen to each other a lot it's
like okay what's the problem and then a
rule there might be well what's the
minimum problem it's like while our
relationship is no good it's like that's
a non-starter for a discussion man
because you can't fix your whole
relationship you have to be more precise
you have to think and maybe your partner
has to help you figure out what it is
that you're upset about right now that
could be rectified I mean maybe you made
a nice dinner or even a dinner that
wasn't so nice and you got treated
casually and with a certain amount of
contempt well everyone was eating it you
know they came in and grabbed the food
scattered to the four ends of the house
and ate it and didn't bring their dishes
back and didn't say thank you and you
know you're very irritated about that
and you have your reasons and you know
the way you might respond to that is
well this relationship isn't working but
it's not precise enough you think well I
have this specific problem I'm trying to
make it a specific problem then I'm
trying to come up with a specific
solution that might make this
relationship this part of the
relationship work better and so look you
have to aim at peace and you have to aim
at love and responsibility and mutual
support you have to want that for the
people that are important to you in your
life and then you can start to talk to
them because you're gonna listen in the
proper way you're gonna listen
in a way that's aiming at that higher
good which is mutual peace amongst the
members of the community something that
I learned for example from Jean Piaget
he called that an equilibrated state and
the collaborated state is like a game
that everyone wants to play and so if
you set your household up properly then
it's a game that everybody is
participating in voluntarily and that's
going to be predicated on the desire for
peace and the willingness to speak truth
and the ability to take responsibility
so that has to be part of your higher
order more lame and then when you're
having a difficult discussion with
someone the discussion is going to be
affected by that higher-order moral aim
it's not going to be contaminated to the
same degree by your desire to inflict
pain and attain victory and you know
crush your opponent and punish them for
their previous sins and indicate your
disappointment things they've done over
the years and all of that and so you can
tell if you've got it balanced by the
way Vincent if the conversation
continues you know when when we used to
sit down for family meetings which
happened on a bi-monthly basis something
like that once every two months
when we return to Davitt divide up
economic and practical duties amongst my
wife and up and I and the kids we had
some rules and the rules were well you
know there's a certain number of things
that have to be done in the house to
keep it running in a manner that anyone
with any sense would want it to run and
there are certain responsibilities that
everyone has to undertake to facilitate
that and there's difficult discussions
that have to be had about who's going to
do what and so here's the rules we have
to make a list of what needs to be done
we have to agree on that and then we
have to each accept the responsibilities
that go along with that in some sort of
order
maybe you
choose one and then I choose one and
then someone else chooses one assuming
that everybody's mature enough and
capable of doing the jobs that they pick
and that you have to negotiate until you
come to the best solution that can be
negotiated which isn't necessarily a
perfect solution but it might be the
best one that can be done and then you
have to stick with it until the next
negotiation and if you get upset during
the negotiations which you likely will
because these are difficult topics how
to divide up responsibilities in the
house and people get mad because they
feel they've been taken advantage of her
are being listened to one of the rules
was well you can leave the discussion
but only until you calm down and then
you have to come back because these
things have to be pushed through they
have to be negotiated through because
the alternative is well important things
don't get done or people do them
resentfully because they're sort of
forced by their own orderliness or their
own conscientiousness or or but we know
by force psychological or otherwise on
the part of other people these things
have to be negotiated through you can
tell if you've got the balance between
making peace and speaking the truth
right if the conversation continues and
it can be emotional and will be and can
be difficult because important things
have to be dealt with but as long as the
people are still in that conversation
and communicating then you then you've
got the balance right you know and you
might have to take a break maybe you
have to hold off till the next day maybe
sometimes when you're negotiating
something that's difficult you have to
offer the other person the opportunity
to sleep on their decision - which i
think is often a very good idea if you
have to make an important decision in
your life it's very useful to tell the
person that you're negotiating with it
look I'm interested in this and it seems
good but I'm not gonna agree until I
sleep on it gives you well lots of
things happen when you sleep you
organize your brain when you sleep at
least to the degree that you can
organize it and you can often be more
solid or more
doubtful about a decision if you sleep
on it so so that's good that's a good
question Vincent dan says I have many
friends but feel lonely from outside I'm
mr. popular yet every single friendship
feels shallow how to transition to fewer
closer friends well it's hard to say
down cuz I don't know the specifics of
your situation and you sound like an
extroverted person and extroverted
people like to be in the center of a
large group of people and you know they
like parties and they like to tell jokes
and they're energized by social
interactions and so they can have a
fairly large group of friends that where
their attention is spread across many
people now and you know that can perhaps
be a contour or one of the consequences
of that can be this feeling that you
have that the friendships are shallow
because there's not much to them the
first question might be well you know do
you have an intimate relationship
because a fair bit of depth of human
interaction comes as a consequence of
long-term committed relationships right
with your wife or your husband or your
parents or your siblings or your
children and so I would say the true
depth in relationship is generally to be
found within family that doesn't mean
that friends aren't important and the
next issue is well are there things that
you're doing with your friends are there
activities that you're undertaking with
your friends that are more significant
than mere casual amusement you know or
is it it's just casual amusement because
if it is you know the bar scene or or
that kind of party
life let's say the friendships aren't
going to be very deep because they're
not they're predicated on shallow
activities and
maybe that you need to find some
activities that you feel are profound on
your own and find people that you can
share them with because a fair bit of
friendship is in fact the engagement in
shared activity and so the more profound
the activity at least in principle then
perhaps the more profound the friendship
certainly the people whose friendships I
would regard as most crucial to me are
people with whom I'm involved in complex
and difficult in endeavors as well as
friendships there are things that we are
doing together that we both regardless
of crucial importance and I think that's
necessary because I think that a fair
bit of friendship apart from you know
the part that's amusement and fun which
is important is a consequence of the
profundity of shared activities and so
you might want to ask yourself you know
are you doing anything with anyone that
you regard is important and and then the
other thing I would ask is well you know
do you have an assortment of intimate
relationships do you have a partner a
wife or a husband do you have children I
don't know how old you are because and
are you spending enough time attending
to your parents and your siblings to
keep those relationships alive with
holidays and with visits and that sort
of thing that's where you find that
relationships that generally speaking
are deep and meaningful and lasting even
though they're often the ones that are
also the most problematic Disney has
taken a direction towards promoting SJW
agendas yes well you can say that again
this has been reflected despite backlash
in the Marvel and Star Wars movies
thoughts my sense is that self-limiting
I mean I know that one of the things
that's I know some people in the comics
industry comic-book industry and I know
that the
superhero types that have been put
forward to manifest a diversity agenda
have generally been colossal failures
and that tends to be the case at the box
office as well and so look here's
something that I think is universally
true as soon as you subvert art and I
would regard movies as art they're a
form of literature and they can be a
very profound form of literature but
even if they're not even if they're you
know like an well paced and well-written
action thriller if the story which is
the art in the movie part of the art in
the movie if the story is subverted to a
political agenda then it's going to be
punished for that at the box-office
because no one except for the odd
acolyte is going to be the least bit
happy with that and even they're not
they'll they'll mouth their approval but
they won't to watch the movies because
they just hear what they they already
know there's no mystery there's no
investigation in a good story the
storyteller should be trying to figure
out the story as he or she writes and
the audience should be participating in
that process the the moral of the story
shouldn't be stamped on the story right
from the beginning because what you have
then is not art you have propaganda and
when people are out to see a movie or to
watch something on television that that
has an artistic a fundamental artistic
nature if it's subverted to propaganda
then it's going to fail
and thank God for that so that's I think
it's self-defeating we'll see there's
nothing that beats a good story you know
there's there's no propaganda that can
compete with a good story so I think
it'll burn itself out
oh here's a simple one what is the soul
to you
that's a hard question I would say like
theologically a soul is that aspect of
the human that aspect of human being
that's akin to divinity that's made in
the image of God and so and I think that
that's a very very important concept I
don't think a society can survive I
don't think that you can survive a
relationship with yourself I don't think
you can have a relationship with another
person and I don't think a society can
organize itself in a productive and
sustainable and peaceful manner without
that idea as the core idea and so the
core idea is that there's something of
irreducible value that characterizes
each human being and that it's of the
highest value which is what makes it say
akin to God or akin to divinity and so
that's the soul and then the question is
maybe how does that manifest itself in
the world so what are its what are its
hallmarks and I would say that that's
very tightly associated with what modern
people describe as consciousness and
there's more to it than consciousness
because it's also character but I would
say character is a manifestation of
consciousness what consciousness does as
far as I can tell is confront unformed
potential this is partly why I think
it's improper I'm writing a fair bit
about this right now in my new book why
it's improper to think of people as
deterministic your deterministic once
you've established a habit and you've
practiced something for a very long
period of time you you become more
deterministic in your actions because
you're expert at reacting and there's
neuro law
chakal neurophysiological circuits that
are laid down to facilitate your action
under those conditions and to run with
some degree of automaticity but most of
the time much of the time what you
confront is the changing future the
future of potential right and it's it's
like a it's like a place of multiple
pathways and your consciousness is that
part of you that confronts those
multiple pathways and decides which one
to walk down and it does so according to
its ethic we talked earlier about the
fact that you need a value hierarchy
it's inevitable that you have a value
hierarchy and that you look at the world
through it and that it should be
well-structured and that there should be
something of divine importance at the
top I would say what should occupy the
top position is the realization for
example that each person is of divine
value and that the most appropriate way
of interacting with potential is by
embodying and speaking the truth that's
not a bad way of briefly conceptualizing
what might be at the highest pinnacle of
the value structure I would say that's
what the logos is and so the soul is a
the soul is what manifests itself in the
choice between different pathways in the
choice between different ways of
transforming the potential of the future
into the actuality of the present and it
does that by making ethical decisions by
choosing between good and evil at each
choice point and to the degree that it
chooses good then it takes the raw
potential of the future and it
transforms it into the being of the
present that is good and to the degree
that it does that in the manner that's
evil and contaminated by malevolence and
hatred and vengefulness then it takes a
pathway that corrupts the world and
makes things worse and
it's the soul that's doing that and it's
the soul that's responsible for that and
it's also that active part of the soul
that shaping the deeper soul in some
sense which would be something like the
cumulative consequence of all those
choices something akin to what people
more classically have referred to as
character now I don't know what the same
really about the metaphysics of the soul
except that it's very mysterious that we
have this capacity for consciousness
which is completely I would say beyond
our current understanding we have no
good reductionist accounts of
consciousness except those put forward
to deny the very existence of something
like consciousness and freewill and the
problem I have with those arguments is
that well the first thing is that you
don't look deterministic until you've
built habits sets and that's a
consequence of consciousness because
consciousness builds habit sets and the
second is that it doesn't seem to be
possible to organize a relationship with
yourself or an intimate partner or a
family or a community without the
concept of the divine value of the
individual and the capacity of that
divine spark let's say to manifest
itself in free will I don't see how
societies can organize themselves
without those principles and to me that
indicates that there's something about
them that's profoundly true now you know
we all have our definitions of what
constitutes sufficient proof for truth
but I think that's powerful those are
those are two powerful arguments so the
it's hard to say what the sole means
metaphysically because you know say
beyond the console on the confines of a
single human being we do have this sense
that the soul can expand itself into
something that's greater than well
greater than it has been it has this
capacity for growth and we do have the
sense that the soul can expand itself to
the point where
it it's enlightened for lack of a better
word that it's working as efficiently as
possible to transform everything that's
unnecessarily painful and malevolent
about the world into what's positive and
good and and and that it does that as a
consequence of confronting the world
with courage and truth and I think
that's right and I do think that that
means that the soul participates in
something eternal which is the attempt
of being itself to transform what's
unnecessarily painful and malevolent
into what's good and that human beings
actually do participate in that and that
that's part of the reason that our
ancient tradition insists that were made
in the image of God and I think that
it's a mistake to underestimate the
importance of that because I don't think
that you can live life a life of
sufficient profundity to protect
yourself from being corrupted by
suffering and malevolence without
adopting a responsibility that's
commensurate with that set of ideas I
think that you either orient yourself
upward you know to the star above the
horizon and try desperately to improve
the structure of being or you work at
counter purposes to it and make things
worse I don't think there's a middle
ground in fact to the degree there is a
middle ground it tilts towards the
negative because people who try to
occupy the middle ground try to
generally try to accrue the benefit
let's say without adopting any of the
risk and that's not acceptable not
helpful
so that's a soul to me and I guess I
would say one more thing about that a
soul is also the center of the world
which is a frightening proposition and
not one that's easily caught
principal Solzhenitsyn's were in the
Gulag Archipelago is particularly
enlightening in this regard because he
insisted that it was a pre preconception
of our judeo-christian heritage that
each person was the center of the cosmos
and you can think of that as a center of
consciousness right center from which
being itself is not only reflected but
also generated and it was Solzhenitsyn's
belief and Dostoyevsky's as well and i
think you would have been in accordance
with this and Nietzsche as well for that
matter that in some manner that we don't
fathom because we don't understand the
structure of the world very well the
outcome of the world is dependent on our
choices and and equally on all of our
choices and I don't understand I know
that's I know that to be true or feel
that to be true
it's it's part of the doctrine that each
person is of intrinsic and equal worth
the part of that doctrine is that each
person is has intrinsic and equal
responsibility and that we're each
capable of generating a fair bit of hell
around us and for other people but also
capable of generating a tremendous
amount of good and that the fate of the
world as it careens through eternity is
actually a consequence of the ethical
decisions of each of us it's a
terrifying idea it's no wonder people
flee from it into hedonism let's say and
and ideology because it's very
frightening possibility that the choices
that you make day to day or fail to make
have this profound and lasting effect on
the structure of reality but I don't
really see any way out of that
conclusion so what are some practical
ways to organize people interested in
reinforcing Western values in culture
without attracting extremists well
that's a good question
reading group might not be a bad idea
you know there's lots of ways of pick a
classic of the Western canon pick
Dante's Inferno or Paradise Lost
something difficult or maybe not or to
try to try something that's more
straightforward I mean Nietzsche's
Beyond Good and Evil is a difficult book
but it's easier than those the two I
just mentioned start a discussion group
start a book group that's that's a
possibility live out your values
properly and see how that works you know
if you're organizing a if you have your
own organization your own business your
own family for that matter you try to
organize it along the principles that
you describe try to organize it for
truth and and along try to organize it
so that it's predicated on truth and
courage and responsibility and the
reduction of unnecessary suffering and
the elimination of malevolence like
seriously do that and see what happens
to your organization I mean I've seen
people now go into large-scale
organizations that were collapsing quite
badly under the weight of accumulated
sins of omission let's say so lies of
failure to attend and to listen to
everyone in the organization these are
large-scale organizations to listen to
everyone in the organization to say look
I'm here to find out what the problems
are you can actually tell me like a real
high alpha male like you know real
empathy you can tell me what the
problems are I want to know what the
problems are and I don't want any I
don't want it it's sugar-coated and the
reason I don't want it sugar-coated is
because I want to know what the problems
are and the reason that I want to know
is because I think that if we face them
we could fix them and that that would be
better for everyone and then to start to
gather information about what it is in
the instance
that's corrupt and functioning
improperly and to start to set it right
and that works and like the evidence for
this I think is solid that it works
there's good evidence that there's a
good book for example called the wealth
and poverty of Nations written by a
Harvard emeritus professor whose name
escapes me momentarily but he talked
about the unbelievably high economic
value of interpersonal trust which I
think is the most fundamental natural
resource and we know too that one of the
best predictors of long-term success in
complex organizations isn't
agreeableness or compassion which is the
only virtue that seems to matter at the
moment even though its status as a
virtue is highly debatable in my
estimation because compassion has to be
temp tempered with judgment
otherwise it's devouring uh-huh but
conscientiousness is an excellent
predictor of long-term success for
individuals and conscientious people are
truthful and reliable and industrious
and orderly you know that can be a
problem because it it can lead to a kind
of rigidity so it's not the only virtue
that's necessary but it does seem to be
the case that honesty is a productive
policy and I would also say that if you
look around the world the cultures that
are the most corrupt are the cultures
that are the most poor and you could say
well the reason that they're corrupt is
because they're poor but I don't believe
that because then you'd have to also
agree that if you're poor you're corrupt
and I don't think that's true
I think the corruption drives the
poverty now there's no doubt somewhat of
a feedback loop there but you get rid of
corruption you get rid of poverty that's
my sense and like like I said you can
make the opposite argument if you want
while poverty causes corruption well
really so your claim is that the poor
are more corrupt because they're poor
that's your fundamental claim and that
the poverty is Drive
the corruption and I'm afraid I don't
believe that I don't think that the poor
there may be more corrupt people who are
poor but that's because they're corrupt
if you take poor people as a group of
people who are relatively deprived
materially I don't believe that there's
any evidence that they are more corrupt
than people who are more materially what
would you call satiated so practical
ways to organize people interested in
reinforcing Western values and cultures
I don't think you have to attract
extremists I think that if you reinforce
Western values and culture you-you-you
turn away the extremists I mean what
sort of extremist is gonna believe in
personal responsibility and and and
individual culpability
those aren't extremist ideas they're
they're anti extremist ideas you can't
group together around the notion of
ultimate personal responsibility so I
think to the degree that you are
reinforcing genuine Western values and
culture you you eliminate the extremists
look you can look at the historical
record you know if I remember correctly
I believe this to be the case no two
democracies have yet gone to war no two
modern democracies have yet gone to war
with one another you know and the
relationship between modern democracy
and high standard of living high
equality of opportunity and and genuine
improvements across the decades I would
say is extraordinarily high and so I
would say intrinsically if you're
promoting Western values the most
fundamental values especially the
doctrine of the sanctity of the
individual and the associated
responsibilities that go along with that
that that just drives the extremists
away
that's my sense of it friendless how to
find friends as traditional woman
attacked by friends I loved by saying
I'm not a feminist and judged saying I
want kids feeling hurt and confused well
that's too bad
really I'm I'm very sorry to hear that
because the idea that you'd be judged
for saying you want it that you want
kids is it's a kind of radical insanity
as far as I'm concerned the first thing
I would suspect is that you're probably
rather young I could be wrong about this
but you know we do everything we can to
delude 19 20 21 year old women into
thinking that there's something
inappropriately patriarchal patriarchal
and subordinate about wanting children
and so many young women are firmly
convinced that the last thing they want
is to have children and they're not
disabused of that foolish notion by
their by their by people who should be
mentoring them properly because the
truth of the matter is the vast majority
of women start to realize in their late
20s and early 30s that there isn't
anything more important to them than
having a family and that's how it should
be that doesn't mean that their careers
aren't important or that career isn't
important it means that family is more
important and if you look at I think it
was the Pew Research Foundation that
recently conducted a poll looking at
what Americans felt brought the most
meaning to their life and what was most
important and I believe it was 76% of
respondents indicated that it was family
and family is more important than career
and you know I say that someone names
they're very grad if
and meaningful career I've done many
things you know I've been a professor
and a clinical psychologist and an
author and many and a businessman I've
I've been involved in an extraordinary
number of high-quality career level
pursuits as well as jobs and I found a
fair share of my fair share of
gratification in those because I like to
work I'm an industrious person but it's
certainly the case that for me my
marriage and my kids have been of
paramount importance and that that
actually becomes more true as I get
older and hopefully wiser and so the
first thing you need to do is stop
feeling guilty about it like you're in
the right you want to have kids more
power to you and if people are telling
you that you know you shouldn't bring
kids into a planet like this or that you
know you're adding to the carbon
footprint of the world you can invite
them politely to step to themselves off
and allow some space for some new life
if they're that concerned about it it's
cruel to speak to women in that manner
as far as I'm concerned to leap to the
conclusion that adding an additional
soul to the world is going to be somehow
harmful when the possibility is very
high that if you have a child and you
raise them carefully that they're going
to have a net positive impact on the
world and that that impact could be
incalculably large and so there's no
there's no excuse whatsoever except a
kind of vicious self-righteous
malevolence that would drive people and
maybe jealousy that would drive people
to insult and belittle a woman who wants
to have children and you know the other
thing you have to realize is that it's
not like you're alone you know every
single one of your ancestress is going
back three
half billion years have children and
that's the way it needs to be any way it
should be and it's a source of
extraordinary deep meaning in life now
if you're gonna have children then you
have the responsibility to do it
responsibly you know and to make it a
priority and to treat it as if it's
important but you need to find some new
friends I would say because these
friends aren't your friends if they're
belittling your admirable desire to do
what everyone who's participated in the
process of continuing life has done
since the beginning of time and anyone
who's anti child is confused so deeply
that they will that that confusion will
definitely cause themselves a tremendous
amount of trouble in their own lives and
the only thing that you can hope for for
people who are that confused is that
they sort it out and decide what's
important before they're too old to make
the right decision and the right
decision is almost inevitably having
children you know I met people who
haven't and I would say it's not easy
for them to fill the void in their life
and these are often people who have had
high-powered careers and it'd be very
successful and admirable people in many
regards but I'll tell you as you get
older that space that your family should
occupy becomes more and more difficult
to fill you need as a person who's
getting older well first of all as a
younger person you need that spark of
life and responsibility that having a
small child brings to you you require
that it matures you because as soon as
you have a child then you're no longer
the more
most important thing in the world and
you're still sadly immature if you're
the most important thing in the world
that's very difficult to get over that
without having a child and then you need
that life and responsibility that the
child provides to bring out the best in
you to to to grow you up and to make you
awake and aware like you might be on
behalf of someone who's fragile and
needs your support and development and
then as you get older well you need to
see life continue to manifest itself in
the possibility of youth and the
adventure that young people go on when
they start a family you need to see that
continuity and it helps ground you in in
the world and gives you hope for not
only for your future but for the for the
future itself and so and then with
regards to saying that you're not a
feminist I guess probably what I would
recommend there is just stop saying that
all it sounds to me like is that it gets
you in trouble I mean I think what you
mean given the way that you wrote your
question is that because you have some
traditional ideas about family it's
difficult for you to reconcile that with
the rhetoric of modern feminism and
that's perfectly understandable because
one the one group that modern feminists
seem to be particularly antipathetic
towards his mother's which is really
quite remarkable achievement given that
they're supposed to be on the side of
women but I would say if you want kids
you talk to people who are positively
inclined to your motivation and ambition
and you don't discuss it with people who
are inclined to put you down and
denigrate that because they're deceiving
themselves they're acting cruelly and
they're doing no-one any favors least of
all themselves and
me not you so you carefully find people
who are willing to support you in your
desire and more power to you as far as
I'm concerned so it's a very courageous
thing to bring a child into the world
you know and then it's a very
responsible thing to do it properly and
you can't grow up you won't grow up and
take your place in the world properly
until you do that and you know it's
certainly possible too that the people
that are attacking you are even
unwilling to come to terms with their
own internal desires that would be my
guess they're denying something that's
they regard as inappropriately
subordinate as I said for for
ideological reasons that to have a child
is to damage the world that would be one
part of it or to subordinate yourself to
the oppressive patriarchy that would be
another part of it and that no alert and
woman would dare to have that as an
ambition but that's so shallow and so
superficial all of that and so self
damaging you know because there isn't
that many things that you have to do in
life that will sustain you in life in a
necessary manner and having a family is
definitely one of those it's maybe half
of your life it might be more than that
but it's definitely at least half your
life you figure intimate relationship
that's a big part of your life your
career and the useful things and
productive things that you do outside
that's another part but fundamentally
fundamentally it's family
paulla how do I stop emotional eating I
am prone to addictive behavior makes me
feel in control I would appreciate your
thoughts on this look Paula the first
thing that I would suggest is that you
probably eat because it makes you feel
better I mean physically so lots of
times I've had clients this has happened
endless numbers of times I've seen it
where people are extremely anxious and
nervous and they eat something and they
feel way better and the reason they feel
better is because well they've either
not been eating enough or they're eating
wrong now I constantly recommend it to
my clients if they were arguing with
their spouses and this is something I
could generally recommend to everyone
that's out there if if the two of you
are involved in a particularly stupid
argument then break and have something
to eat have some cheese have some have
something that's protein and fat heavy
like a snack and wait 10 minutes and
then talk again and see you might find
that you're endlessly more reasonable
and so I would also say generally
speaking Paula you should eat a fat and
protein heavy breakfast and a lot of it
probably more than you want probably
more than you would feel comfortable
with it's the most important meal of the
day and it's possible that your
dysregulated psycho physiologically so
that if you get stressed your body over
produces insulin and takes all the blood
sugar out of your out of your blood
system and that makes you anxious and
and irritable and makes it difficult for
you to think and then if you eat
something and it could be something
sweet although I wouldn't recommend that
because it's a bad medium to long term
solution if you eat something you
probably feel way better like literally
not psychologically so the trick there
is to eat a big breakfast and then not
allow you
self to get hungry during the day you
know so eat three meals make them a
decent size and if you need to carry a
snack or something like that nuts are
really useful can be really useful if
you can tolerate them or something like
beef jerky which i think is actually
better so try that try eating a big
breakfast and then try not letting
yourself get hungry and see if that
so-called emotional eating decreases now
what you could do along with that is see
to what degree you can decrease your
intake of carbohydrates and sugar
because that may be causing you a lot of
trouble and I would say if you are
inclined to eat emotionally don't eat
carbohydrates and sugar because it'll
fix it temporarily but it'll make it
worse like an hour later so assume a
problem with eating habit before you're
assuming a psychological problem so
I'm a Silicon Valley founder and find
that whatever happens here happens
elsewhere fast what can we do and you do
to start by the entity politics here
well don't play the identity politics
game no diversity initiatives no
inclusivity initiatives no equity
initiatives no quota no discussion of
systemic racism none of the tropes that
are associated with politically with the
radical political left because to the
degree that you let any of that into
your organization you let it all in and
so higher on the basis of competence
using objective tests and let the cards
fall where they're going to and don't be
afraid to tell people that that's what
you're doing
watch your HR department carefully and
make sure that they're not pushing
diversity inclusivity and equity
initiatives that they're not requiring
people to take implicit association test
that hypothetically reveal their
unconscious bias that they're not doing
seminars on systemic racism and
Prejudice and then they're not making
the assumption that unequal outcomes
let's say in terms of hiring in the STEM
fields or in terms of employment in the
STEM fields which by the way are
radically overestimated if you unless
you gerrymander what constitutes the
definition of a stem discipline you just
have to you have to not participate in
any of that and you have to make it
known to your peers which would be other
Silicon Valley founders I would presume
that you're not doing any of that and so
that's the that's the best advice that I
have is don't start playing the game and
really keep an eye on your HR people
because that's their new pathway to
unearned power and influence and not of
an appropriate sort so you know you
might think as well what your values are
I don't mean in a mish
statement sort of way because I tend to
think that that's often casual to the
point of virtue signaling but you know
you need to think through what sort of
organization that you want to have and
what the principles are going to be and
make those clear as an alternative story
to the diversity inclusivity and equity
rhetoric so that's what I would
recommend
dan I habitually procrastinate on
important tasks CV writing for example
for months on end waiting for the right
time
it is severely holding me back how to
avoid this
well I covered that in Chapter four and
twelve rules for life so you could read
that that would help
it's called comparing yourself to who
you were yesterday instead of who
someone else is today look if you're
procrastinating on your CV writing then
you're biting off more than you can chew
and I would say to some degree it's a
reflection and I don't mean this in a
pejorative way it's a reflection of a
lack of humility you think you're
capable of taking on larger tasks than
you actually are and the proof of that
is in what you said you take on these
large tasks and then you don't complete
them so obviously you're not capable of
taking on the large tasks and completing
them so with regards to CV writing you
you have to sit down and negotiate with
yourself you have to ask yourself like
seriously okay I need to do something
about this CV I need to at least start
it because obviously you're not going to
finish it unless you start it and then
you have to ask yourself like you're
asking someone that you don't know and
that you can't negotiate with very well
what you might be willing to do like so
if you come to see a behavior therapist
and and the problem was well I can't get
started on my CV the therapist might say
well why don't you just bring your CV
next week and we'll take a look at it
just just uh you know bring it rough
form don't all you have to do is
download and on disk or email it and
then the person may or may not do that
and if they don't do it well then you
have to find out huh then you may have
to say okay well I notice you didn't
email mice your CV to me this week so
how about this how about we make an
appointment by phone tomorrow at 10:30
and I'll phone you or you phone me and
you'll be
on your computer and you'll go through
your files with me and then you'll email
me the CV do you think you can do that
and then usually people will manage that
but maybe they come back the next week
and they haven't even done that and so
then you say well look why don't next
week why don't you bring your computer
or your disk and we'll go through it
together and find your CV and bring it
up on screen and just take a look at it
you know because actually a CV is quite
a daunting thing to work on because it's
your whole past and your whole future
and so it's a pretty big dragon the
trick is to find a piece of the solution
that you would be willing to engage in
that you would actually do and so you
know I might also recommend to one of my
clients that all they do is go onto
their computer and find out which folder
their CV is in and open it just open the
file or sorry open the folder and then
if they that'd be one day's work is just
go open the folder and then maybe the
next day is well drag the file onto your
desktop so it's there and then maybe the
next day's job just open it just open it
and just like glance at the first page
and then close it and I know this seems
ridiculous because you think well I'm an
adult and I should be able to do more
than that and maybe you can but it
sounds like you can't so you have to
start where you can start and I also
recommend to my clients that once they
make themselves a deal about what
they're gonna do they stick to it so if
the deal is well I'm just going to drag
the file with my CV in it onto my
desktop and that's today's task I'm not
going to open start working on it
because once you make a deal with
yourself especially with regards to
something you're afraid of and you're
avoiding if you push yourself farther
than what you've negotiated with
yourself honestly then you'll find that
you won't get back to the work because
you don't trust your negotiating
abilities anymore
you don't trust yourself so if the deal
is you drag the file onto the desktop
and that's today's job and that's a lot
better because it's more than you've
done for two months then you give
yourself a pat on the back and you say
look good enough man like it's no big
act of heroism that I can go out show
about in the street but I'm farther
ahead than I was and then well then
maybe the next day's task is well read
it just read it just familiarize
yourself with it again close it good
enough then you can think that night
well where are the holes what needs to
be updated then the next thing might be
to do to say well here's a list of 20
things that might need to be done with
this CV and you know they don't all have
to be that accurate but you might have
some sense of what it need what needs to
be updated where the holes are and you
know where it ends and what you'd have
to do to get the information necessary
to update it and that that's a good time
to talk to someone else about it too and
then you can rank order those 20 things
in terms of the probability that you'll
do them the same way break them down
into small subtasks and and maybe you
can only work on it for 10 minutes a day
cuz it stresses you out so badly god
only knows what's hiding behind your
fear of your CV you know you might be
embarrassed about your past
accomplishments you might be unwilling
to do the work because your CV hasn't
been updated for a long period of time
there might be holes in your CV that you
don't know how to account for you
reading your CV might make you realise
that you're in the wrong job it might
bring up the specter of having to look
for new employment you know a CV is a
real monster because it's a record of
your life and a guide to your future
ambition so if you happen to be afraid
of it well you should take it seriously
it's not just a piece of paper it's a
real dragon and so then you face it to
the degree that you can face it and you
break it down two steps you break it
down you break down the steps that are
necessary until they're so small that
even someone as avoidant as you is
likely to make progress and then you
find your natural speed
of advancement and perhaps over a month
you can put your CV together and then
congratulations to you because it's a
hard thing and you know you'll find to
that a lot a lot of fears are associated
with that like oh no now I'm gonna if I
finish this I'm gonna have to send it
out and if I'm gonna send it out I'm
gonna have to look for another job and
if I'm gonna look for another job I'm
gonna have to move and who knows what
that'll do to my relationship and who
knows if anybody wants to hire me and
god only knows if I'll be successful in
my new career and so there can be a
tremendous number of subordinate fears
associated with something as simple as
oh I need to update my CV which is a
really easy thing to say but a very
difficult thing to do so I would say
have a little bit of compassion for
yourself like not enough so that it
stops you from moving forward or gives
you an excuse but do decompose the
problem into small elements that you can
handle and be humble enough not to be
too irritated at yourself when you find
out just how small those pieces have to
be in order for you to successfully
master them
and I think that's where I'm gonna stop
guys I'm I'm out of intelligent things
to say I would say and starting to get
somewhat tired and there's a lot of
extremely sophisticated and complicated
questions here that I'd like to continue
answering but not today
and so thank you very much for tuning in
if you're in London UK you might think
about coming to my talk at the Apollo on
May 8th I'm gonna be at Oxford around
then too and I don't know if I'll be
giving a talk then that's still in
negotiation but I'll definitely be at
the Apollo as I said my paperback is
coming out in the UK in early May so
that's exciting
I'm signing a bunch of front pages for
the paperback we're still planning a
European tour in September that will be
announced relatively soon if we can get
all the details straight and I'll see
those of you who are coming to see me in
New York I'll see you in April and also
at this level is G ship debate in
Toronto on the 19th and so thank you
very much for your continued support and
for tuning in to the QA and it was a
pleasure to answer your questions and
have the opportunity to talk about
serious issues and in that in a careful
and thoughtful manner with all of you so
good night